Guide to the Vardan Hovhannisyan video collection AD.MC.001
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Videos
  - Public funerals of Armenian militia fighters, part 1 (05:45), circa winter 1990; ad_barswar1_019_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 33 MB (Object 31)
    Public funeral ceremony for several soldiers killed in fighting, whose uniformed bodies are displayed on funeral biers, draped in flags of Nargorno-Karabakh (Artsakh), before procession moves through streets of unidentified city.Unidentified location, likely Nagorno-Karabakh, circa winter 1990. Time: 05:45
  - Public funerals of Armenian militia fighters, part 2 (32:39), circa winter 1990; ad_barswar1_019_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 186 MB (Object 32)
    Public funeral ceremony for soldiers killed in fighting, may be continuation of previous footage, showing burial of caskets and graveside ceremonies, including playing of trumpet, firing of weapons. Footage shifts to steps of building, with armed soldiers, Orthodox priests, and crowd raising clenched fists and flowers, along with a funeral biers containing another dead soldier being held aloft, before the crowd proceeds with him to the cemetery for the burial. Time: 32:39
  - Soviet military base in Caucasus, and interviews with soldiers and civilians (26:03), circa 1990; ad_barswar1_020_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 148 MB (Object 33)
    Winter, military base for Soviet forces, likely in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa 1990. Exterior of base, arrival of Soviet troop convoy. Footage shifts to interviews of a villager, as well as Soviet soldiers, asking their opinions about the cause of the conflict and currentconditions. Time: 26:03
  - Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan, with adresses by Levon Ter-Petrosyan and unidentified Belgian member of the European Parliament (16:38), March 1990; ad_barswar1_021_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 94 MB (Object 34)
    Protest event, Freedom Square, Yerevan, 30 March 1990. Several speakers, including Levon Ter-Petrosyan, address the conflict in Nagorno-Karabakh. Also includes an unidentified member of the European Parliament, from Belgium, who addresses the right of national self-determination, referencing the Flemish separatist movement in his native Belgium, and expressing solidarity with Armenians. Time: 16:38
  - Public funeral for Armenian militia fighter, part 1 (13:45), circa 1990; ad_barswar1_022_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 78 MB (Object 35)
    Public funeral service for a soldier, with family members and other soldiers at graveside, raising clenched fists, while family mourns over open casket of soldier. Undated, circa 1990. Various speakers make remarks in support of nationalism, independence of Nagorno-Karabakh, and similar comments. Mourners file by casket to pay last respects. Time: 13:45
  - Public funeral for Armenian militia fighter, part 2 (03:59), circa 1990; ad_barswar1_023_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 22 MB (Object 36)
    Public funeral service for soldier, continuation of previous tape, as soldier's casket is lowered into the grave, and mourners leave the cemetery. Time: 03:59
  - Rally and march in Yerevan, commemorating 75th anniversary of Armenian genocide (19:24), April 1990; ad_barswar1_024_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 110 MB (Object 37)
    Rally and procession in Yerevan, 24 April 1990, marking the 75th anniversary of the Armenian genocide. March begins in Freedom Square, and proceeds to the Tsitsernakaberd genocide memorial, where those present place flowers at thememorial. Time: 19:24
  - Tsitsernakaberd memorial to victims of Armenian genocide, nightime procession and ceremony (07:45), ad_barswar1_024_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 44 MB (Object 38)
    Tsitsernakaberd memorial to victims of Armenian genocide. Nighttime, likely continuation of previous film footage, 24 April 1990, as people pay their respects at the memorial. Some are interviewed about their opinions regarding independencefor Armenia. Time: 07:45
  - Clash between Armenian militia and Soviet military forces, Yerevan and Nubarashen, part 1 (15:22), May 1990; ad_barswar1_025_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 88 MB (Object 39)
    Soviet military forces in Yerevan, 27 May 1990. Begins with police ordering people to leave, and tanks, trucks, and armored personnel carriers departing from the central railway station and proceeding down streets. Cameraman (Hovahnissyan) attempts to interview military personnel in these vehicles, and is prevented from doing so. Time: 15:22
  - Clash between Armenian militia and Soviet military forces, Yerevan and Nubarashen, part 2 (08:56), May 1990; ad_barswar1_025_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 39 MB (Object 40)
    Soviet military forces in Yerevan, 27 May 1990, appears to be continuation of previous footage, with cameraman following military vehicles, and then filming aftermath of violent clashes at the railway station, including bullet holes in buildings, clean-up of debris, blood on ground. Eyewitnesses describe what had happened, and that victims were Armenians. Time: 08:56
  - Clash between Armenian militia and Soviet military forces, Yerevan and Nubarashen, part 3 (14:23), May 1990; ad_barswar1_025_03_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 82 MB (Object 41)
    Scope and Contents
    Further footage of clashes between Armenian militia and Soviet troops, likely from 27 May 1990, in Sovetashen (now Nubarashen), an outlying district of Yerevan. Footage includes people fleeing from sounds of gunfire, Soviet tanks rolling over hillsides, wounded being evacuated by ambulance, and militia walking through the streets. Time: 14:23
  - Clash between Armenian militia and Soviet military forces, Yerevan and Nubarashen, part 4 (30:23), May 1990; ad_barswar1_025_04_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recordings 172 MB (Object 42)
    Continuation of footage from clashes between Armenian militia and Soviet troops, Yerevan, 27 May 1990. Includes footage of aftermath of clash at central railway station, and presence of Soviet troops on surrounding streets. Footage of Armenian militia on outskirts, likely Nubarashen, in standoff with Soviet forces, and cameraman (Hovahnissyan) fleeing when gunfire breaks out, and subsequent drive through streets of Yerevan. Time: 30:23
  - Clash between Armenian militia and Soviet military forces, Yerevan and Nubarashen, part 5 (46:31), May 1990; ad_barswar1_026_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 265 MB (Object 43)
    Public funeral for several Armenians, likely those killed in the clashes with Soviet troops in Yerevan, May 1990. Includes open caskets of women and men who were killed in the fighting, attended by mourners, and procession to church. Time: 46:31
  - Protest and hunger strike outside building of Supreme Soviet of the Armenian S.S.R., Yerevan (06:12), circa winter 1990; ad_barswar1_028_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 35 MB (Object 44)
    Protest outside of the building of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the Armenian S.S.R., in Yerevan, circa winter 1990. Includes footage of man (Hayk Mehrabyan) conducting a hunger strike, and banners hung on and near building protesting the Soviet presence in Armenia. Time: 6:12
  - Levon Ter-Petrosyan addressing rally at Freedom Square, Yerevan (02:57), circa spring 1990; ad_barswar1_029_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 17 MB (Object 45)
    Levon Ter-Petrosyan, head of the Pan-Armenian National Movement, speaking to a rally on Freedom Square, Yerevan, circa spring 1990. Discusses the perception of the Soviet government toward the Armenian separatist movement, and the motives for their opposition to it. Time: 2:57
  - Protest outside building of Supreme Council of Ministers, during debate on self-government, part 1 (27:28), circa spring-summer 1990; ad_barswar1_030_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 155 MB (Object 46)
    Segment begins with vehicles in funeral procession, may have been for victims of clash with Soviet troops of 27 May 1990. Continues with footage of protest in front of the building of the Council of Ministers in Yerevan, and then a separate clip of Soviet military vehicles, personnel carriers, on roadside. Remaining clips show crowd in front of Council of Ministers building, listening to broadcast proceedings of debate going on inside, and their reactions, interspersed with footage from inside the building as various speakers, including Levon Ter-Petrosyan, discuss proposed elections and steps to be taken toward forming a government. Undated, circa spring-summer 1990. Time: 27:28
  - Protest outside building of Supreme Council of Ministers, during debate on self-government, part 2 (09:17), circa spring-summer 1990; ad_barswar1_030_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 53 MB (Object 47)
    Continuation of last footage, showing delegates who had been inside the Council of Ministers building, exiting and being greeted by jubilant crowds. Biggest response is when Ter-Petrosyan exits and mingles with the crowd. As he enters a car to leave, the cameraman (Hovahnissyan) gets into another car and follows Ter-Petrosyan through the streets of Yerevan to his next destination. Time: 9:17
  - Outdoor protest, Kiev, Ukrainian S.S.R. (43:20), ad_barswar1_031_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 245 MB (Object 48)
    Ukraine, likely Kiev. Various clips of exhibition, vendors of nationalist buttons and flags, and outdoor protest related to the nuclear accident at Chernobyl. Crowd is assembled in front of a church, whose bells toll. A succession of speakers, accompanied by Orthodox priests, who perform the liturgy, address the crowd. At the end, candles are lit and placed on the ground, with pictures of loved ones. Time: 43:20
  - Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan (28:25), circa March 1990; ad_barswar1_032_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 160 MB (Object 49)
    Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan, circa March 1990. Several speakers, including those calling for Armenian expatriates to return to their homeland in order to help build the country. Includes addresses from Armenian nationalist leaders, as well as Soviet or Communist Party leaders, the latter addressing the crowd in Russian (rather than Armenian). Time: 28:25
  - Vandalism of statue of Lenin, Republic Square, Yerevan (05:10), circa early 1990; ad_barswar1_033_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 29 MB (Object 50)
    Republic Square, Yerevan, circa early 1990. Footage showing graffiti, paint splotches, other vandalism, on statue of V.I. Lenin. Crowds of onlookers in front of statue, talking, as well as soldiers laughing and talking, are also included in footage. Time: 5:10
  - Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan (10:18), circa 1989-1990; ad_barswar1_034_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 58 MB (Object 51)
    Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan, undated, circa 1989-1990. Includes prayers for nation, and calls for greater democracy and for unification with Nagorno-Karabakh. Time: 10:18
  - Riga, Latvia. Aftermath of armed insurrection by Soviet sympathizers, opposed to Latvian independence (09:58), January 1991; ad_barswar1_035_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 56 MB (Object 52)
    Riga, Latvia. Aftermath of fighting between forces advocating for Latvian independence, and Soviet sympathizers. Undated, but could be from events of January 1991. Depicts damage from attack on a government building located on Rudolf Endrupa steet, Riga, a Latvian militiaman guarding that building, and a burned-out car nearby. Candles and flowers are placed on the building plaque for the Latvian Ministry of the Interior, which had been a target of the January 1991 attacks. Other scenes show demonstrators at night, and others building barricades in the following days. Time: 09:58
  - Footage of village, presumably in Nagorno-Karabakh (02:33), Undated, circa 1990; ad_barswar1_036_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 15 MB (Object 53)
    Village, perhaps in Nagorno-Karabakh. Footage primarily of cameraman (Hovhanissyan) seated in a vehicle, filming as it travels through village and surrounding countryside, following another vehicle. Undated, circa 1990. Time: 02:33
  - Armenian militia in Nagorno-Karabakh, and interviews with Soviet soldiers (22:58), Undated, circa 1990; ad_barswar1_036_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 129 MB (Object 54)
    Soldiers, likely Armenian militia in the conflict in Nagorno-Karabakh. Footage is likely continuation of previous segment. Soldiers at lookout post, villagers tending their garden plots, at well, returning from bakery, and being interviewed by cameraman, describing life in village as they are at war with Azerbaijanis in neighboring village. Also includes footage of and interviews with Soviet soldiers stationed near village. Time: 22:58
  - Armenian militia in village in Nagorno-Karabakh, with doctor discussing treatment of wounded soldiers (26:13), Undated, circa 1990; ad_barswar1_036_03_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 149 MB (Object 55)
    Village, likely in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa 1990. Appears to be continuation of previous two segments. Interview with doctor discussing difficult conditions, need for more medical supplies and doctors. Funeral procession in village, appears to be for a militia member killed in fighting, followed by funeral service in church, and procession with casket to hilltop where casket is loaded onto a helicopter, along with another wounded man, for transport elsewhere. Also includes footage of Armenian militia members firing upon Azerbaijani forces across a distant field. Time: 26:13
  - Armenian militia firing on Azerbaijani forces in Nagorno-Karabakh (11:58), Undared, circa 1990; ad_barswar1_036_04_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 68 MB (Object 56)
    Continuation of previous footage, of Armenian militia firing on Azerbaijani forces in the distance, Nagorno-Karabakh, undated, circa 1990. Time: 11:58
  - Aftermath of fighting in unidentified city in Nagorno-Karabakh (01:02:02), Undated, circa winter 1990; ad_barswar1_037_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 351 MB (Object 57)
    Aftermath of a battle in a city, presumably Nagorno-Karabakh, undated, circa 1990. Depicts heavily damaged or destroyed apartment buildings, civilians in a hospital, corpses. Civilians walking through city, seeking to fill canisters with water or fuel. Buildings damaged or on fire following shelling. Time: 1:02:02
  - Village, unknown location, presumably Nagorno-Karabakh (01:22), Undated; ad_barswar1_038_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 7.7 MB (Object 58)
    Village, and people walking and seated. Unidentified location, undated. Time: 01:22
  - Hospital or shelter, in unidentified location, possibly Azerbaijan (08:34), ad_barswar1_038_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 45 MB (Object 59)
    Women in what appears to be a hospital or shelter, possibly Azerbaijani, being questioned by someone. Ambulances arriving and departing from building, in one case bringing wounded soldiers. Children assembled outside building in a group, being entertained by street performers. Time: 08:34
  - Public funeral, likely for militia fighter (16:48), Undated, circa 1990; ad_barswar1_038_03_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 96 MB (Object 60)
    Public funeral, likely for a fallen soldier, in a cemetery within a city, likely related to previous two segments. Procession to another location in town, groups of people, soldiers and civilians, waiting. Unidentified, circa 1990. Time: 16:48
  - Gandzasar monastery and village of Vanq, and militia fighters stationed nearby (31:08), Undated, circa 1993; ad_barswar1_038_04_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 177 MB (Object 61)
    Gandzasar monastery and the village of Vanq, circa 1993. View of exterior of monastery, repairs being made to buildings. Separate footage of children and adults in nearby village, wounded soldiers in hospital, and soldiers at recreation outside town, including watching performance of traditional dances and music, and swimming in a lake. Time: 31:08
  - Village, perhaps Vanq; airlift evacuation of wounded soldiers and civilians, and protest in Yerevan (25:50), Undated.; ad_barswar1_038_05_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 147 MB (Object 62)
    Continuation of previous footage. Soldiers and civilian women dancing to traditional music, in location outside of town. Next footage consists of people boarding an Aeroflot helicopter, medical evacuation of wounded soldiers as well as accompanying civilians. Includes footage of trip over nearby terrain, arrival in distant location. Footage shifts to people gathering for a march in Yerevan, and back to life in a village, perhaps in Nagorno-Karabakh, with footage of elderly women, children. Undated. Time: 25:50
  - Village in Nagorno-Karabakh, with footage of soldiers and civilians (17:53), Undated, circa June 1993; ad_barswar1_038_06_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 101 MB (Object 63)
    Village, likely in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa June 1993. Women and children outdoors, couple, including husband in military uniform, talking in their apartment; soldiers gathering in front of building, being loaded into troop transports. Time: 17:53
  - Armenian militia, fighting in Nagorno-Karabakh (59:58), Undated, circa 1993; ad_barswar1_038_07_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 341 MB (Object 64)
    Soldiers, likely Armenians fighting in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa 1993. At night by campfire, rising in the morning to breakfast, waiting, being loaded onto troop transports. Men watching smoke rising from distant hillsides. Time: 59:58
  - Aerial evacuation of civilians to Stepanakert (04:19), Undated, circa 1993; ad_barswar1_038_08_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 25 MB (Object 65)
    Aeroflot helicopter, evacuating people, mostly civilians, and a casket, to Stepanakert, circa 1993. On arrival and disembarking, mourning and crying. Time: 04:19
  - Town in Nagorno-Karabakh (25:34), Undated, circa 1993-1994; ad_barswar1_039_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 145 MB (Object 66)
    Footage of town, likely in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa 1994. Women and children, bloodstained stretchers used to transport wounded, lined up outside building, civilians repairing park, unused playground. Time: 25:34
  - Town in Nagorno-Karabakh, in aftermath of fighting (06:09), Undated, circa 1993-1994; ad_barswar1_040_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 35 MB (Object 67)
    Footage of town, likely in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa 1993-1994. Unidentified location. Travelling by truck through town, footage of burning buildings, military convoy passing farmer pushing his belongings and chickens on a wheelbarrow by the side of the road. People evacuating town using farm vehicles, push carts. Some are filmed passing a destroyed tank, sitting in the middle of the road. Soldiers in another tank see it, stop, inspect it, then fire weapons into the air and place flowers on it, likely signaling they found deceased comrades inside it. Time: 06:09
  - Interviews with Azerbaijani children, about experiences of war (15:28), Undated, circa early 1990s; ad_barswar1_041_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 88 MB (Object 68)
    Azerbaijani children being interviewed about their experiences of war, their families, and of their fathers who are fighting in the war. Also includes a young Azerbaijani man being held captive by the Armenians. Undated, circa early 1990s. Time: 15:28
  - Interview with young Azerbaijani man, about experiences of war (01:19), Undated, circa early 1990s; ad_barswar1_041_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 7.7 MB (Object 69)
    Continuation of interview with young Azerbaijani man, from last segment. Time: 01:19
  - Interviews with young Azerbaijani man, and with children (13:17), Undated, circa early 1990s; ad_barswar1_041_03_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 75 MB (Object 70)
    Continuation of previous two segments, with same interviewees. Young man has learned Armenian, has lived in Armenia in camps for over a year, and states that Azerbaijan has made a mistake in waging war. Additional younger children are also Interviewed. Footage includes young boy smiling while playing with a gun. Time: 13:17
  - Interviews with Azerbaijani children and youth (01:04:15), Undated, circa early 1990s; ad_barswar1_041_04_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 366 MB (Object 71)
    Continuation of previous segments, of interviews with several children and adolescents. Time: 1:04:15
  - Wedding festivities, Nagorno-Karabakh (35:41), circa 1990s; ad_barswar1_042_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 204 MB (Object 72)
    Traditional Armenian dancing and music, at what appear to be wedding festivities, unidentified location, likely in Nagorno-Karabakh, circa early 1990s. Includes procession along a village street, banquet room, people eating and talking, followed by musical performances and dancing, and toasts being made to soldiers fighting in the war. Time: 35:41
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), part 1 (15:48), December 1988; ad_barswar1_043_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 90 MB (Object 73)
    Footage shot from vehicle (likely bus), travelling through devastated region of Armenia, near and in Leninakan, following the earthquake of December 1988. Onboard the bus, people from Leninakan (Gyumri) point out where certain buildings used to stand. Many ruined buildings are depicted, along with tent encampments, military vehicles and personnel. Also shows excavation of collapsed buildings, and interview with Russian speaking soldier, who describes arrival of army troops to aid in the excavation, as well as desire of Armenians serving elsewhere in the Red Army who wished to return and aid in the effort. Time: 15:48
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), part 2 (38:19), December 1988; ad_barswar1_043_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 217 MB (Object 74)
    Continuation of previous footage, showing tent encampments, foreign (American) search and rescue workers with dogs, recovery of earthquake victims from collapsed buildings, and mourning family members, circa December 1988. Time: 38:19
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), part 3 (01:16), December 1988; ad_barswar1_044_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 7.2 MB (Object 75)
    Winter landscape, village with snow covered mountains in background, near Leninakan (Gyumri), Armenia, along with newly-built hospital, circa December 1988. Time: 01:16
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), part 4 (01:53), 1988-1989; ad_barswar1_044_02_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 11 MB (Object 76)
    Earthquake damage in city, likely Leninakan (Gyumri). Filmmaker interviews (in Armenian) a family of seven, living in temporary quarters, next to ruined building. The family expresses doubt that they will receive an apartment to replace their destroyed one. Circa December 1988- early 1989. Time: 01:53
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), part 5 (04:57), 1988-1989; ad_barswar1_044_03_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 28 MB (Object 77)
    Winter landscape, scenes of city (Leninakan) at foot of snow-covered mountains, damaged buildings viewed from a distance, may be continuation of footage in tape 75. Circa 1988-1989. Time: 04:57
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), part 6 (07:47), December 1988; ad_barswar1_044_04_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 44 MB (Object 78)
    Damage from earthquake, with footage of buildings in Gyumri (Leninakan), including the main post office, images of city center, convoys of trucks, people walking the streets, selling food, circa December 1988. Time: 07:47
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), (03:37), December 1988; ad_barswar1_044_05_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 21 MB (Object 79)
    Continuation of footage of destruction from December 1988 earthquake near Gyumri (Leninakan) and Spitak. Views of apartment buildings, churches, including one that had been built by Americans, street life, and winter landscapes. Time: 03:37
  - Ceremony on anniversary of Armenian genocide, Yerevan (Tsisternakaberd) (13:15), circa 1995; ad_barswar1_045_01_800k_s.mp4; 1 video_recording 74 MB (Object 80)